A Finding Aid to the Maryette Charlton papers, circa 1890-2013, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Maryette Charlton papers
circa 1890-2013
Archives of American Art
Charlton, Maryette
AAA.charmary
Archival Resource Key
80.6 Linear feet
0.34 Gigabytes
The papers of filmmaker, photographer, painter, printmaker, teacher, and arts advocate Maryette Charlton measure 81 linear feet and date from circa 1890 to 2013. This particularly rich collection includes biographical materials, correspondence, writings, 30 diaries, teaching files, professional and project files, major film project files, artist research files, exhibition files, printed material, scrapbooks, artwork, 22 sketchbooks, extensive photographic materials, numerous sound and film recordings, a digitized sound recording, and an unintegrated later addition to the papers containing additional biographical materials, journals, correspondence, subject files, printed materials, and scattered photographs.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged as 16 series.
Missing Title
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1896-2005 (3.4 linear feet; Boxes 1-4, 80)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1930-2010 (23.3 linear feet; Boxes 4-27, 80)
Series 3: Writings, 1942-1999 (1 linear feet; Boxes 27-28)
Series 4: Diaries, 1943-2001 (2.1 linear feet; Boxes 28-30)
Series 5: Teaching Files, 1946-1997 (3.6 linear feet; Boxes 30-33, 80)
Series 6: Professional and Project Files, 1923-1998 (7.6 linear feet; Boxes 34-41, 81, OV 87)
Series 7: Artist Research Files, 1949-circa 2000 (1.8 linear feet; Boxes 41-43, FCs 88-89)
Series 8: Major Film Projects, 1904-2007 (18.8 linear feet, 0.34 GB; Boxes 43-61, 81-82, OV 87, FC 90-91, ER01)
Series 9: Exhibition Files, 1950-2000 (0.8 linear feet; Boxes 61-62)
Series 10: Printed Material, 1924-2000 (3.2 linear feet; Boxes 62-65, 82, OV 87)
Series 11: Scrapbooks, 1939-2010 (0.8 linear feet; Box 65, 82-83)
Series 12: Artwork, 1950-1998 (0.9 linear feet; Boxes 65-66, 84)
Series 13: Sketchbooks, 1949-1996 (0.5 linear feet; Box 66)
Series 14: Photographic Materials, circa 1890-circa 2010 (7.8 linear feet; Boxes 67-74, 84-86)
Series 15: Sound and Video Recordings, circa 1953-2008 (1.2 linear feet; Boxes 74-75, 86)
Series 16: Addition to Maryette Charlton papers, 1951-2013 (3.7 linear feet; Boxes 75-79, 86)
Biographical / Historical
Maryette Charlton (1924-2013) was a painter, printmaker, photographer, filmmaker and arts advocate based in Chicago, Illinois, and New York, New York.
Maryette Charlton was born in Manchester, Iowa on May 18, 1924. Her parents were Shannon and Etna Charlton and she had 2 siblings. Charlton pursued her undergraduate studies at Monticello College and Northwestern University in Illinois, Antioch College in Ohio, and the University of Colorado before receiving a B.F.A. from Pratt Institute in Brooklyn, New York in 1947. She continued her studies in Chicago, Illinois with Laszlo Moholy-Nagy and Hugo Weber at the Institute of Design and Art Institute of Chicago. From 1948 to 1952, she was a Department of Education lecturer at the Art Institute of Chicago museum galleries and also gave talks at schools for the Chicago Public School Art Society.
Between 1942-1951, Maryette Charlton worked as a color analyst for the Container Corporation of America. In 1952, Charlton founded the Art Department of the American University of Beirut and taught there as an assistant professor until 1956. While in Beirut, Charlton married photographer Hall Winslow in 1953 and their only child Kirk Winslow was born in 1955. Winslow and Charlton later divorced in 1973.
Charlton moved to New York City in 1955. She began a master's program at Columbia University and graduated with a M.F.A in film and printmaking in 1958.
Charlton made numerous documentary films, mostly about American artists including Alexander Calder, e. e. cummings, Jeanne Reynal, Dorothy Miller, Pierre Matisse, Lenore Tawney, and Loren MacIver. She also worked tirelessly to promote the work of sculptor, architect, and set designer Frederick Kiesler. She was the camera woman for Kiesler's Kiesler's Universal Theater which aired on CBS in 1962. She became close friends with Kiesler's widow, Lillian, and they collaborated on the film Kiesler on Kiesler and numerous other film and art projects, supporting the work of young artists. Charlton also worked on commissioned films, including The Mosaics of Jeanne Reynal and Zen in Ryoko-in. Charlton befriended many artists in the visual, literary, and film worlds, including Elizabeth Bishop, Dimitri Hadzi, Margo Hoff, James Purdy, and Delphine Seyrig.
A performer in her own right, Charlton appeared in the works of Richard Foreman, Jo Andres, and others. She also played the part of Helen Keller in the film Ghostlight (2003).
An Iowa native, Charlton founded the University of Iowa Museum of Art together with Leone and Owen Elliott. She maintained a close relationship with the Iowa Museum over many years as a donor and chronicler.
Charlton died in New York City on November 25, 2013.
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Contact Reference Services for more information.
Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Existence and Location of Copies
Some of the video and sound recordings in this collection have been copied for research access and are available in the Archives of American Art offices.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Maryette Charlton papers were donated in multiple accretions from 1998-2011 by Maryette Charlton, and in 2013-2014 by the Maryette Charlton estate via Jo Andres, executor.
Related Materials
The Houghton Library at Harvard University and the University of Iowa Museum of Art also hold papers and artwork by Maryette Charlton. The Museum of Modern Art, New York, houses the film Kiesler on Kiesler, created by Maryette Charlton.
The Archives of American Art also has the papers of Frederick and Lillian Kiesler, a portion of which was donated by Charlton.
Scope and Contents
The papers of filmmaker, photographer, painter, printmaker, teacher, and arts advocate Maryette Charlton measure 81 linear feet and 0.34 gigabytes and date from circa 1890 to 2013. This particularly rich collection includes biographical materials, correspondence, writings, 30 diaries, teaching files, professional and project files, major film project files, artist research files, exhibition files, printed material, scrapbooks, artwork, 22 sketchbooks, extensive photographic materials, numerous sound and video recordings, motion picture film, a digitized sound recording, and an unintegrated later addition to the papers containing additional biographical materials, journals, correspondence, subject files, printed materials, and scattered photographs.
Biographical materials consist of material on Maryette Charlton and her family. The subseries on Maryette Charlton includes a biographical chronology, passports, records of her marriage to Hall Winslow, information on studio spaces, school transcripts, and other material. Family files include genealogical charts and files of family members containing correspondence, writings, printed material, sound and video recordings, and photographs. The bulk of the family files are for Charlton's parents, Etna and Shannon, and her husband and son, Hall and Kirk Winslow.
Extensive correspondence is with family, friends, artists, and colleagues. Family correspondence is with her husband and son, parents, and extended family. Personal correspondence is with friends and colleagues, many of whom were famous artists. Named correspondence files and chonological correspondence files contain exchanges with Jo Andres, Elizabeth Bishop, Xenia Cage, Paula Court, Yasuo Fujitomi, Dimitri Hadzi, Margo Hoff, Sylvia Shaw Judson, Lillian Kiesler, Cindy Lubar, Loren MacIver, Pierre Matisse, Nimet (Saba Habachy), Henri Seyrig, Robert Wilson, and many others. There is also correspondence with colleges, museums, and universities.
Writings include academic papers and college class notes, titled essays, a notebook with sketches, and miscellaneous notes. Thirty diaries cover the period 1943 - 2001 and document a wide variety of topics, from film projects to travels to the art world in New York City. Some diaries are illustrated, including one illustrated by Alexander Calder at a party with Maryette, Ellsworth Kelly, and actress Delphine Seyrig. Journals from 1978-1979 tell of Charlton's experiences while appearing in films made by avant-garde director Richard Foreman. There is also one diary of Maryette's mother Etna Barr Charlton.
Teaching files document Charlton's career as an instructor at the Art Institute of Chicago and as the founder of and instructor at the American University of Beirut's art department. Files include appointment calendars, schedules, notes, lectures, news releases, printed material, and photographs.
Professional and project files consist of material related to Maryette Charlton's professional work at the University of Iowa Museum of Art, as a lecturer at the Chicago Public School Art Society, color analyst at the Container Corporation of America, executor of the estate of artist Louise Medbery von Brockdorff, fellowships, conferences, organizations, and the filming industry in general. There are files for the screening of Zen in Ryoko-In. The University of Iowa Museum of Art subseries consists of correspondence with fellow co-founders Leone and Owen Elliott, files on art donations, museum administration, annual reports, printed material, photographs, and sound and video recordings.
Artist research files consist of books, articles, and clippings collected by Charlton for research. Notable artists chronicled include Alexander Calder, James Purdy, Louise Nevelson, Kiki Smith, and Toshiko Takaezu.
Major film project files document Maryette Charlton's films about or with artists Frederick Kiesler (Trienniale, The Universal Theater and Kiesler on Kieseler), Lenore Tawney, Dorothy Miller, Loren MacIver, and Jeanne Reynal. The files for Frederick Kiesler also contain materials about his wife Lillian Kiesler, with whom Charlton had a long relationship and collaborated with on film projects. Individual film project files contain a wide variety of research and production documentation, including correspondence, writings, printed material, research files, exhibition catalogs, photographic materials, sound recordings of interviews and lectures, and Charlton's documentation about the creation and producation of each film, such as contracts, scripts, and distribution information. The film project files for Kiesler and Dorothy Miller are particularly rich, containing substantial amounts of primary source materials not found elsewhere. Sound and video recordings are found throughout the series, as well as 4 film reels.
Files documenting Maryette Charlton's group and solo exhibitions include catalogs and announcements, publicity, printed material, mailing lists, art inventory, sales lists, correspondence, and other material.
Printed materials include other exhibition catalogs, books, posters, magazines, and clippings. There are many books on color theory from Maryette Charlton's job as a color analyst and substanial printed material on Frederick Kiesler. Scrapbooks document Maryette Charlton's personal life from high school, college, and summer camp, as well as exhibitions of her own work, and miscellaneous subjects.
Artwork includes sketches and drawings by Maryette Charlton, some drawings by Lillian Kiesler and others, and mail art created by various artists. There are also 22 sketchbooks filled with pencil, ink, and crayon drawings and sketches, with occasional annotations.
Photographic materials include photographs, slides, negatives, and photograph albums. There are photographs of Maryette Charlton, her travels, family, friends, and artists. Photographs are also found throughout other series.
Sound and video recordings which could not be merged with other series were arranged in an audiovisual series. There are recordings of radio programs and performances Maryette Charlton attended or participated in as well as miscellaneous recordings of artists and events.
The 2014 addition to the Maryette Charlton papers consists of biographical materials, journals, correspondence, subject files, printed materials, and a small number of photographs.
Filmmakers -- New York (State) -- New York; Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Printmakers -- New York (State) -- New York; Photographers -- New York (State) -- New York; Art teachers -- New York (State) -- New York; Museums -- Administration; Women artists; Women painters; Women photographers; Women printmakers; Women educators; Art -- Study and teaching; Color; Photographs; Diaries; Sketchbooks; Sketches; Interviews; Scrapbooks; Sound recordings; Scripts (documents); Drawings; Mail art; Motion pictures (visual works); Video recordings; Fujitomi, Yasuo, 1928-; Habachy, Nimet; Elliott, Leone; Elliott, Owen; Tawney, Lenore; Von Brockdorff, Louise Medbery; Hadzi, Dimitri, 1921-2006; Haskins, Sylvia Shaw Judson, 1897-; Hoff, Margo; Andres, Jo; Kiesler, Lillian, 1910?-2001; Kiesler, Frederick; Calder, Alexander, 1898-1976; Court, Paula; Bishop, Elizabeth, 1911-1979; Cage, Xenia; Matisse, Pierre, 1900-1989; Miller, Dorothy Canning, 1904-2003; Lubar, Cindy; MacIver, Loren, 1909-; Reynal, Jeanne, 1903-; Smith, Kiki, 1954-; Nevelson, Louise, 1899-1988; Purdy, James; Art Institute of Chicago -- Faculty; Takaezu, Toshiko; American University of Beirut -- Faculty; Chicago Public School Art Society; University of Iowa, Museum of Art; Container Corporation of America
- Biographical Material, 1896-2005; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 3.4 Linear feet Boxes 1-4, 80
  Scope and Contents
  Biographical material consists of records about Maryette Charlton's personal life, academic studies, and family history.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged as 2 subseries.
  Missing Title
  1.1: Maryette Charlton, 1938-2005
  1.2: Family Files, 1898-2003
  - Maryette Charlton, 1938-2005; 1.1; Archival Resource Key
    The subseries on Maryette Charlton includes a biographical chronology, passports, records of her marriage to and divorce from Hall Winslow, information on studio and work spaces, school transcripts and diplomas, yearbooks, a pilot's license and manuals from when she took flying lessons, and other material. There is one videocassette and one sound tape reel.
    - Maryette Charlton Biographical Chronology, 2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
    - Passports, 1952-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Manchester High School, Archival Resource Key (Box 1)
      - Freshman Year, 1938-1939; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Sophmore Year, 1939-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Junior Year, 1940-1941; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
      - Senior Year, 1941-1942; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
      - Photographs, 1938-1942; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - "Manchester High School Reunion", 1987; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Reunions, 1987-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Monticello College Freshman Year, 1942-1943; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Monticello Echo, 1943; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Flying Lessons, Archival Resource Key (Box 1)
      - Flight Manuals and Notes, 1941-1943; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Pilot's License and Flight Log Book, 1943; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Photographs, 1943-1944; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Printed Material, 1943-1946; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Art Institute of Chicago Evening School, 1943-1944; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - YWCA Chicago Address Books and Miscellaneous, 1943-1944; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Pratt Institute Academic Transcript, 1947; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Wedding Announcements, 1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
    - Ox-Bow Summer School of Painting, 1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Columbia University Course Catalogs and Clippings, 1958-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Columbia University Diploma, 1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Apartments, Archival Resource Key (Box 2)
      - 56 Seventh Avenue, New York City, 1979-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - 131 East 19th Street, New York City, 1959-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - 148 Front Street, New York City, 1956-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - 148 Front Street, New York City, 1982-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - 289 Seventh Avenue, New York City, 1966-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - 317 Second Avenue, New York City, 1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Studio 18J, 77 Seventh Avenue, New York City, 1978-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - Studio 336 West Schiller Street, Chicago, 1951-1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Separation and Divorce, 1970-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17-19)
    - Maryette Charlton Interview on WUNY-FM Broadcast, 1976 September 30; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Maryette Charlton Transcript of WUNY-FM Interview, 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - University of Iowa Presidents Club Plaque, 1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 22)
      Oversized material housed in Box 80
    - Oversized Presidents Club Plaque from Box 2, folder 22, 1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 80)
  - Family Files, 1896-2003; 1.2; Archival Resource Key
    This subseries includes assorted material on genealogical history, family reunions, events, and relatives. The bulk of the material consists of records on Maryette Charlton's parents, Etna and Shannon, and her husband and son, Hall and Kirk Winslow, with a few files on other extended family members. There is biographical material, correspondence, writings, printed material, and photographs. There are also 6 videocassettes, 2 sound cassettes, and 1 sound tape reel.
    - Thanksgiving, 1969; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - "Family Addresses" List, 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Beam-Charlton Family Genealogy, 1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Charlton Family History, 1970-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Charlton Family Reunion, 1991; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Charlton, Etna Barr, Archival Resource Key (Box 2)
      - Autobiography, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 28)
      - Correspondence, 1917-1936; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Charlton, Etna Barr, Archival Resource Key (Box 3)
      - Postcards and Greeting Cards, 1937-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - Illness, 1979-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Memorial, 1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Condolence Letters, 1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
      - Book Inventory, 1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - Photographs, 1896-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - Photographs, 1918-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - Photographs with Shannon Charlton, circa 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - Miscellaneous Material, 1971-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Charlton, Shannon B., Archival Resource Key (Box 3)
      - Biographical Material, circa 1910-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 11)
      - Correspondence, 1900-1937; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Condolence Letters, 1969-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - News Clippings, 1912-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 14)
      - Clippings, 1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - Funeral and Obituaries, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 16)
      - Printed Material, 1981-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 17)
      - Photograph Printing Plate and Portraits, circa 1935; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 18)
      - Photographs, circa 1900-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 19)
      - Photographs, circa 1908-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 20)
      - Photographs, circa 1910-circa 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Charlton, William Stuart, 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Charlton-Winslow Beirut Seaside Apartment, 1953-1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Hoag-Barr Family Histories, 1970-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - McMillan, Wayne, 1935-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Moore, Elizabeth Charlton, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Winslow, Hall, Archival Resource Key (Box 4)
      - Resumes, 1956-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Writings, 1944-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Article on Sherrille Stroud, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Exhibition Catalog and Announcement, circa 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Servas International, 1992-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - Photography Exhibit Scrapbook, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - Photography Exhibit Scrapbook, 1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Winslow, Kirk, Archival Resource Key (Box 4)
      - Framed Check Signed by Willem de Kooning, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - Scrapbook of Printed Material on Clouds, circa 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 12)
      - Condolence Phone Call Messages, 2002; Archival Resource Key; 2 Sound cassettes (Box 4, Folder 13)
      - Maryette Charlton's Notes on Calls about Kirk Winslow, 2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 14)
      - Notes on "Maryette Charlton's Calls to Friends" After Kirk Winslow's Death, 2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 15-16)
      - "Kirk Winslow Tribute at PS 122", 2003 March 10; Archival Resource Key; 2 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 4, Folder 17)
      - "Kirk Winslow Tribute at PS 122", 2003 March 10; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (MiniDV); 2 Videocassettes (Hi8) (Box 4, Folder 18)
      - Auction Catalogs, 1984-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 19)
      - Baby Album, 1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Oversized Etna Barr Charlton Photograph from Box 3, Folder 7, 1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 80)
- Correspondence, 1930-2010; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 23.3 Linear feet Boxes 4-27, 80
  Correspondence is with family, friends, artists, and colleagues.
  2.1: Family Correspondence, 1930-2002
  2.2: Personal Correspondence, 1938-2010
  - Family Correspondence, 1930-2002; 2.1; Archival Resource Key
    The alphabetical correspondence files are first, followed by roughly sorted chronologically ordered folders.
    Maryette Charlton's family correspondence is with her husband and son, Hall and Kirk Winslow, her parents and extended family members. There is 1 sound cassette.
    - Camp Good Health, 1942; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 21)
      Letters by Maryette Charlton to her parents.
    - McMillen, Wayne, 1939-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Monticello College, 1942-1943; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Vail, Colorado Family Reunion, 1991; Archival Resource Key; Includes 1 sound cassette. (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
    - Wedding Correspondence, 1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 3)